Last Updated: May 4, 2020

Summer 2017, 18, 19

JOSHUA S. SPEAGLE

Harvard University Department of Astronomy joshspeagle.github.io | jspeagle@cfa.harvard.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the interdisciplinary fields of astrostatistics and data science at the intersections of astronomy, statistics, and computer science. My research focuses on using large datasets to better understand how galaxies like our own Milky Way form, behave, and evolve.

POSITIONS

Dunlap Postdoctoral Fellow: Dunlap Institute, University of Toronto	2020-present
Banting Postdoctoral Fellow: University of Toronto	2020-present
Project Academic Support Staff: Kavli IPMU, University of Tokyo	2015-2016

EDUCATION

Harvard University: PhD in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Doug Finkbeiner & Charlie Conroy (with Daniel Eisenstein & Alyssa Goodman)	
Harvard University: MA in Astronomy	2016-2020
Advisers: Daniel Eisenstein (with Alexie Leauthaud; UCSC)	
Harvard University: BA in Astrophysics and Physics	2011-2015

AWARDS & HONORS

Eric R. Keto Prize for Best Thesis in Theoretical Astrophysics (Harvard)	2020
Banting Postdoctoral Fellowship	2020
Department of Astronomy Teaching Award (Harvard)	Spring 2018
Bok Center Certificate of Distinction in Teaching (Harvard)	Spring 2017, 18; Fall 2018
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship	2016

TEACHING

I have a strong interest in education and pedagogy, with a focus on skills such as **programming**, **statistics**, and data science that are invaluable across a wide range of disciplines but too often not taught as part of a typical science curriculum.

Harvard: Teaching Fellow

ASTRON 22: The Unity of Science: From the Big Bang to the Brontosaurus and Beyond	Spring 2020
ASTRON 191: Astrophysics Laboratory	Spring 2019
ASTRON 17: Galactic and Extragalactic Astronomy	Fall 2018
ASTRON 130: Cosmology	Spring 2018
ASTRON 16: Stellar and Planetary Astronomy	Spring 2017

Banneker Institute (Harvard): Course Instructor

Introduction to Programming in Python

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Founder and Organizer: CfA Machine Learning Journal Club

Manuscript Referee: ApJ, ApJL, AJ, A&A, MNRAS

2017-2020

2014-present

RECENT PRESENTATIONS

Villanova: Colloquium

October 2019

Exploring the Galaxy Near and Far in the Age of Gaia

Harvard: Summer Colloquium (joint with Catherine Zucker)

June 2019

Charting Nearby Molecular Clouds with Gaia: A New Map of Our Local Interstellar Medium

GitHub Satellite 2019: Keynote Address Participant

May 2019

Invited for open source code contributions (dynesty) in the analysis of the supermassive black hole in M87 by the Even Horizon Telescope collaboration

Cambridge: Data Intensive Science Seminar

April 2019

Mapping the 3-D Distribution of Dust in the Milky Way with Stellar Photometry

Harvard: CMSA Big Data Conference

August 2018

Revealing the Milky Way's Dust-iny

Bayes Comp 2018: Poster

March 2018

Dynamic Nested Sampling with dynesty

UMass Amherst: Data Science Tea

October 2017

Big Data Inference: Combining Hierarchical Bayes and Machine Learning to Improve Photometric Redshifts

PUBLICATIONS

I am an author of **35 papers**, including **10 as (co-)first author** (in **red**) and **12 where I have made substantial contributions** (in **blue**). My papers have over **2000 citations** (<u>h-index=17</u>), including over **700 citations** (<u>h-index=7</u>) for papers where I am (co-)first author.

My papers can be found online on arxiv and ADS.

In Preparation

- 37. Speagle, J. S.; Zucker, C.; Cargile, P. A.; Bonaca, A.; Johnson, B. D.; Beane, A.; Kamdar, H.; Dotter, A.; Naidu, R.; Han, J.; Conroy, C.; Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Rix, H.-W.; Ting, Y.-S.; Goodman, A.; & Eisenstein, D. J.

 Mapping the Milky Way in 5-D with 170 Million Stars at High Galactic Latitudes
- **Speagle, J. S.**; Zucker, C.; Cargile, P. A.; Johnson, B. D.; Beane, G.; Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Dotter, A.; Bonaca, A.; Naidu, R.; Han, J.; Conroy, C.; Rix, H.-W.; Ting, Y.-S.; Goodman, A. A.; & Eisenstein, D. J.

Deriving Stellar Properties, Distances, and Reddenings from Photometry and Astrometry with brutus

Under Review

No papers currently under review.

- 35. Cabrera-Ziri, I.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Dalessandro, E.; Usher, C.; Bastian, N. J.; Salaris, M.; Martocchia, S.; Kozhurina-Platais, V.; Niederhofer, F.; Lardo, C.; & Larsen, S. S., **MNRAS**Searching for Globular Cluster Chemical Anomalies on the Main Sequence of a Young Massive Cluster arxiv: 2004.09636
- 34. Bonaca, A.; Conroy, C.; Hogg, D. W.; Cargile, P. A.; Caldwell, N.; Naidu, R. P.; Price-Whelan, A. M.; **Speagle, J. S.**; & Johnson, B. D., **ApJL**High-Resolution Spectroscopy of the GD-1 Stellar Stream Localizes the Perturber Near the Orbital Plane of Sagittarius

 arxiv: 2001.07215
- 33. Leja, J.; Speagle, J. S.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Franx, M., ApJ

 A New Census of the 0.2 < z < 3.0 Universe, Part I: The Stellar Mass Function

 arxiv: 1910.04168
- 32. Portillo, S. K. N. & Speagle, J. S.; & Finkbeiner, D. P., AJ Photometric Biases in Modern Surveys arxiv: 1902.02374
 Press: AAS
- 31. Speagle, J. S., MNRAS

 dynesty: A Dynamic Nested Sampling Package for Estimating Bayesian Posteriors and Evidences
 arxiv: 1904.02180
- 30. Alves, J.; Zucker, C.; Goodman, A. A.; Speagle, J. S.; Meingast, S.; Robitaille, T.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; Schlafly, E. F.; & Green, G. M., Nature

 Discovery of a Galactic-scale gas wave in the Solar Neighborhood

 arxiv: 2001.08748

 Press: Official Website
- 29. Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M.; Finkbeiner, D. P., Goodman, A.; & Alves, J., A&A
 A Compendium of Distances to Molecular Clouds in the Star Formation Handbook arxiv: 2001.00591

2019

28. Speagle, J. S., arxiv

A Conceptual Introduction to Markov Chain Monte Carlo Methods arxiv: 1909.12313

- 27. Green, G. M.; Schlafly, E. F.; Zucker, C.; Speagle, J. S.; & Finkbeiner, D. P., ApJ A 3D Dust Map Based on Gaia, Pan-STARRS 1 and 2MASS arxiv: 1905.02734
- 26. Huang, S.; Leauthaud, A.; Hearin, A.; Behroozi, P.; Bradshaw, C.; Ardila, F.; **Speagle, J.**; Tenenti, A.; Bundy, K.; Greene, J.; Sifón, C.; & Bahcall, N., **MNRAS**Weak Lensing Reveals a Tight Connection Between Dark Matter Halo Mass and the Distribution of Stellar Mass in Massive Galaxies

arxiv: 1811.01139

Press: CfA Science Update

- 25. Speagle, J. S.; Leauthaud, A.; Huang, S.; Bradshaw, C. P.; Ardila, F.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Mandelbaum, R.; More, S.; Simet, M.; & Sifón, C., MNRAS Galaxy-Galaxy Lensing in HSC: Validation Tests and the Impact of Heterogeneous Spectroscopic Training Sets

 arxiv: 1906.05876
- 24. Namikawa, T. et al. [73 additional co-authors], ApJ

 Evidence for the Cross-correlation between Cosmic Microwave Background Polarization Lensing from POLARBEAR and the Cosmic Shear from Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam

 arxiv: 1904.02116
- 23. Forbes, J. C.; Krumholz, M. R.; & **Speagle, J. S., MNRAS**Towards a Radially-Resolved Semi-Analytic Model for the Evolution of Disc Galaxies Tuned with Machine Learning

 arxiv: 1810.12919
- 22. Cook, B. A.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

 Measuring Star-Formation Histories, Distances, and Metallicities with Pixel Color-Magnitude

 Diagrams I: Model Definition and Mock Tests

 arxiv: 1904.00011
- 21. Safarzadeh, M.; Berger, E.; Leja, J.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJL

 Measuring the Delay Time Distribution of Binary Neutron Stars III. Using the Individual Star

 Formation Histories of Gravitational Wave Event Host Galaxies in the Local Universe

 arxiv: 1905.04310

 Press: AAS NOVA
- 20. Hikage, C. et al. [35 additional co-authors], PASJ

 Cosmology from cosmic shear power spectra with Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam first-year data arxiv: 1809.09148
- 19. Leja, J.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; van Dokkum, P.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Brammer, G.; Momcheva, I.; Skelton, R.; Whitaker, K. E.; Franx, M; & Nelson, E. J., **ApJ**An Older, More Quiescent Universe from Panchromatic SED Fitting of the 3D-HST Survey arxiv: 1812.05608
- 18. Zucker, C. & Speagle, J. S.; Schlafly, E. F.; Green, G. M., Finkbeiner, D. P.; Goodman, A. A.; & Alves, J., ApJ
 A Large Catalog of Accurate Distances to Local Molecular Clouds: The Gaia DR2 Edition arxiv: 1902.01425
- 17. Leja, J.; Carnall, A. C.; Johnson, B. D.; Conroy, C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ How to Measure Galaxy Star Formation Histories II: Nonparametric Models arxiv: 1811.03637

16. Zucker, C.; Schlafly E. F.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Green, G. M.; Portillo, S. K. N.; Finkbeiner, D. P.; & Goodman, A. A., **ApJ**

Mapping Distances Across the Perseus Molecular Cloud Using CO Observations, Stellar Photometry, and Gaia DR2 Parallax Measurements

arxiv: 1803.08931

15. Medezinski, E.; Oguri, M.; Nishizawa, A.; **Speagle, J. S.**; Miyatake, H.; Umetsu, K.; Leauthaud, A.; Murata, R.; Mandelbaum, R.; Sifón, C.; Strauss, M. A.; Huang, S.; Simet, M.; Okabe, N.; Tanaka, M.; & Yutaka, K., **PASJ**

Source Selection for Cluster Weak Lensing Measurements in the Hyper Sprime-Cam Survey arxiv: 1706.00427

14. Mandelbaum, R. et al. [30 additional co-authors], PASJ

The first-year shear catalog of the Subaru Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey arxiv: 1706.06745

13. Tanaka, M.; Coupon, J.; Hsieh, B.-C.; Mineo, S., Nishizawa, A. J.; Speagle, J.; Furusawa, H.; Miyazaki, S.; & Murayama, H., PASJ

Photometric Redshifts for the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program Data Release 1 arxiv: 1704.05988

12. Aihara, H. et al. [108 additional co-authors], PASJ

First Data Release of the Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program arxiv: 1702.08449

11. Aihara, H. et al. [142 additional co-authors], PASJ

The Hyper Suprime-Cam SSP Survey: Overview and Survey Design arxiv: 1704.05858

10. Oguri, M. et al. [24 additional co-authors], PASJ

An optically-selected cluster catalog at redshift 0.1<z<1.1 from Hyper Suprime-Cam Subaru Strategic Program S16A data

arxiv: 1701.00818

2017

9. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps II. Implementation arxiv: <u>1510.08080</u>

8. Speagle, J. S. & Eisenstein, D. J., MNRAS

Deriving Photometric Redshifts with Fuzzy Archetypes and Self-Organizing Maps I. Methodology arxiv: $\underline{1510.08073}$

2016

7. Speagle, J. S.; Capak, P. L.; Eisenstein, D. J.; Masters, D. C.; Steinhardt, C. L., MNRAS

Exploring Photometric Redshifts as an Optimization Problem: An Ensemble MCMC and Simulated

Annealing-Driven Template-fitting Approach

arxiv: 1508.02484

6. Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; Masters, D. C.; & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

The Impossibly Early Galaxy Problem

arxiv: 1506.01377

2015

5. Masters, D. C. et al. [19 additional co-authors], ApJ

Mapping the Galaxy Color-Redshift Relation: Optimal Photometric Redshift Calibration Strategies for Cosmology Surveys

arxiv: <u>1509.03318</u>

2014

4. Steinhardt, C. L. & Speagle, J. S., ApJ

A Uniform History for Galaxy Evolution

arxiv: <u>1409.2883</u>

3. Steinhardt, C. L.; Speagle, J. S. et al. [22 additional co-authors], ApJL

Star Formation at 4 < z < 6 from the Spitzer Large Area Survey with Hyper-Suprime-Cam (SPLASH)

arxiv: <u>1407.7030</u>

Press: IPL

2. Speagle, J. S.; Steinhardt, C. L.; Capak, P. L.; & Silverman, J. D., ApJS

A Highly Consistent Framework for the Evolution of the Star-Forming Main Sequence' from z~0-6

arxiv: 1405.2041

2011

1. Speagle, J. S.; Kaplan, D. L.; & van Kerkwijk, M. H., ApJ

The X-ray Counterpart of the High-B Pulsar J0726-2612

arxiv: 1111.2877